Eugene, OR, 97403

pgromano | mpgromano

Summary_

My research has focused on developing reliable theoretical/computational models to investigate the role of stochastic fluctuations in protein-DNA complexes. I've studied this by analyzing atomistic long timescale macromolecular simulations and performing unsupervised learning via Markov State Models.

Programming Python, Fortran+F2PY, Cython, C++, Bash, Matlab **Data Analysis** NumPy, Scikit-Learn/Image, SciPy, Pandas, Matplotlib

MD Simulations GROMACS, Amber Languages Fluent English & Spanish

Education

St. Edward's University

B.S. IN CHEMISTRY WITH A MINOR IN MATHEMATICS

Aug. 2008 - May. 2012

- Welch Research Grant (2010-11). Given to Chemistry & Biochemistry students who perform novel research.
- Brother Daniel Lynch Research Award (2011). Provides support to senior students engaged in research projects who excel in academics and community service.
- President's Scholar Award (2008–12). For academic merit reviewed recurrently every semester.

University Of Oregon

PH.D. IN PHYSICAL CHEMISTRY

Sep. 2012 - Exp. Sep. 2017

- · Promising Scholar Award (2012). Award offered to a select group of incoming graduate students in recognition of their academic excellence in expectation of the unique perspectives they will bring to campus.
- · Molecular Biology Biophysics Traning Grant (2014-16). NIH training grant awarded yearly through the University of Oregon's Institute of Molecular Biology. The objective is this award being to facilitate training to prepare graduate students to work on important problems in molecular biology and biophysics. This is accomplished by collaboration between multifaceted research programs. A full list of explanation can be found at http://molbio.uoregon.edu/molbio-training-grant/.

Research Experience _____

University of Oregon

MARINA GUENZA LAB

Sep. 2012 - Sep. 2017

Research efforts focused on modeling the conformational dynamics of DNA unstacking/unwinding mechanism, a key physical process involved in thermally induced breathing fluctuations that allow accessibility in protein recognition. To model the slow barrier crossing inherent in rare event transition, microsecond Molecular Dynamics (MD) simulation were analyzed by Markov State Models (MSM) which build a network of stochastic transitions between discrete states along the coordinates of slow-order parameters.

St. Edward's University

EAMONN HEALY LAB

Jan. 2009 - Jun. 2012

Structural studies comparing ADAM10 and ADAM17 to study drug potency and selectivity. The ADAM family is a class of enzymes largely linked to inflammatory response in pathologies such as rheumatoid arthritis and metastasis in cancers. Due to the large homology both in sequence and conformation in the active site, drugs targeting ADAM17 typically result in favorable selectivity towards several other members of the ADAM family, leading to side effects. Docking studies were performed using methods within Accelrys Discovery Studio to structurally evaluate novel acetylenic based inhibitors that targeted structural motifs and the associated dynamics found in ADAM17 but not ADAM10.

Teaching Experience _____

St. Edward's University Department of Chemistry

Austin, Texas

LAB TEACHING ASSISTANT

Aug. 2010 - Jun. 2012

- · Assisted in laboratory course work for General Chemistry, Organic Chemistry I & II, and Biochemistry.
- · Responsibilities included giving lab lectures, assisting in desiging lab coursework, and preparing and standardizing stock reagent.

Pablo G. Romano MAY 18, 2017

St. Edward's University Academic Success Center

Austin, Texas

Supplemental Instructor

Aug. 2010 - Jun. 2012

- · Assisted in course work in General Chemistry, Organic Chemistry I & II, Analytical Chemistry, and Biochemistry.
- Expectations for the position involved holding office hours and leading two weekly group study lectures as a supplement to to coincide with course work

University of Oregon Department of Chemistry

Eugene, Oregor

GRADUATE TEACHING FELLOW

Sep. 2012 - Sep. 2014

- Assisted in laboratory course work for General Chemistry I, II, & III.
- Work expectations involved weekly office hours, assisting in theory based lectures, leading and lecturing course experiments, assisting in course
 examinations, and grading lab coursework.

University of Oregon Department

Eugene, Orego

Undergraduate Research Mentor

Sep. 2012 - Sep. 2014

- · Trained and mentored undergraduates in research and computational methods.
- Students were trained to run Molecular Dynamics (MD) simulations using Gromacs.
- Visualization used PyMol and Visual Molecular Dynamics software.
- Additional requirements for mentorship involved teaching students to use Linux operating systems, giving a 2 hour course on Research Ethics, and conducting weekly research review sessions to help students develop proper research methods.

University of Oregon Department of Chemistry

Eugene, Ored

NONEQUILIBRIUM STATISTICAL MECHANICS

- Sep. 2016
- Week long lecture series on non equilibrium statistical mechanics focused on applications Markov State Models (MSM) of biological macro-molecules.
- The series presented up to date theory, development of the field, and provided a hands-on learning module using the Python and PyEMMA software package.
- · Students built MSMs for protein folding simulations.

Presentation & Workshops_

American Physical Society: National Meeting

New Orleans Louisiana

CHIRAL PATHWAYS IN DNA DINUCLEOTIDES USING GRADIENT OPTIMIZED REFINEMENT ALONG METASTABLE BORDERS

Mar. 2017

 Presented talk on novel method for refining of Markov State Models. The method used underlying probability distribution to correct undersampling while retaining crisp boundaries.

Centre Européen de Calcul Atomique et Moléculaire

Iulich, Germany

CECAM Macromolecular Simulation Software Workshop

Oct. 2015

- "Hackathon" workshop with the aim of tackling the most challenging problems within macromolecular modeling, particularly those relating to how the capabilities of and opportunities presented by future generations of massive heterogeneous, computational resources can best be leveraged in this domain of science.
- Travel expenses were funded by travel fellowship awarded to promising US candidates.

Biophysical Society: National Meeting

altimore, Maryland

ANALYZING SMALL DNA CONSTRUCTS VIA A CHROMOPHORE MODEL WITHIN THE POINT DIPOLE APPROXIMATION.

Mar. 2015

 Presented poster on ensemble model to predict the Circular Dichroism spectra of small oligonucleotide constructs employing a classical point dipole approximation.

American Chemical Society: National Meeting

ndianapolis, Indiand

COARSE-GRAINING AND MULTISCALE MODELING IN COMPLEX CHEMICAL SYSTEMS

• Attended conference for development of academic and research pursuits.

Sep. 2013

• Travel expenses were funded by a NSF Phase 1 Center for Chemical Innovation. Fellowship awarded to underrepresented minorities students in the STEM field.

American Chemical Society: Southwest Regional Meeting

New Orleans, Louisiand

ACETYLENIC INHIBITORS OF ADAM10 AND ADAM17: IN SILICO ANALYSIS OF POTENCY AND SELECTIVITY

Sep. 2012

· Presented talk on comparative study on binding potency and selectivity effects for inhibitors targeting TACE protein family.

Program Committees _____

Physical Chemistry Faculty Search

University of Oregon

Organizer & Host

2016

Hosted lunch series aimed to introduce students to faculty candidates.

• Students had the opportunity to learn about research and working in Academia.

Pablo G. Romano 2 May 18, 2017

Organizer & Host 2015-2016

- Hosted a series of lunches aimed to introduce students to invited Physical Chemistry Speakers.
- Students had opportunity to learn about research

Publications

The Gradient Adaptive Decomposition (GRAD) method: Optimized refinement along macrostate borders in Markov State Models

PG Romano, M Guenza; J. Chem. Info. & Mod.

Submitted

Chiral Stacking Transition Pathways in DNA Oligonucleotides

PG Romano, M Guenza; J. Chem. Phys.

In Preparation

Markov State Models for DNA using a Langevin Approach

PG ROMANO, M GUENZA; J. BIOPHYS.

'n Preparatior